<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Death and the grave no bar to believers happiness, or, A sermon preached at the funerall of the Lady Honor Vyner, in the Parish Church of Mary Wolnoth in Lombardstreet, July 10, 1656 by William Spurstow ...</title>
            <author>Spurstowe, William, 1605?-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61204</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5092</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13492</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13586921</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13586921</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100568</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61204)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100568)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 851:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Death and the grave no bar to believers happiness, or, A sermon preached at the funerall of the Lady Honor Vyner, in the Parish Church of Mary Wolnoth in Lombardstreet, July 10, 1656 by William Spurstow ...</title>
                  <author>Spurstowe, William, 1605?-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Rothwell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Vyner, Honor, --  Lady, d. 1656.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XVII, 15 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100568:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100568:1"/>
            <p>DEATH AND THE GRAVE <hi>No Bar to Believers Happineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OR, A SERMON preached at the Funerall OF THE <hi>Lady</hi> HONOR VYNER, In the Pariſh Church of <hi>Mary Wolnoth</hi> in <hi>Lombardſtreet,</hi> July 10. 1656.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM SPURSTOW, D. D. and Miniſter of Gods Word at <hi>Hackney.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>If in this life onely we have hope in Chriſt, we are of all men moſt miſerable,</q>
            <bibl>1 Cor. 15. 19.</bibl>
            <q>I will ranſome them from the power of the grave, I will redeem them from death: O death I will be thy plague; O grave, I will be thy deſtruction,</q>
            <bibl>Hoſea 13. 14.</bibl>
            <p>
               <hi>Omnia ſub ſole vanitas; ergo ſupra ſolem veritas.</hi> Paulin. in Opuſc.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Rothwell,</hi> at the Fountain in Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths-row in <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:100568:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100568:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFULL <hi>Sir</hi> THOMAS VYNER, <hi>K<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> And Alderman of the City of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince that you are pleaſed not to be disſatisfied with the long ſtay of this Sermon, it matters not to give an account to others, to whoſe hands it may happily come, what the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are that have made it to ſtick ſo long in the birth. And yet I am willing they ſhould underſtand thus much: Firſt, that it is a <hi>ſad work,</hi> and that I never preached or printed more unchearfully: Sorrow is a paſſion that moves ſlowly, it makes the words ſlow as well as few,
<pb facs="tcp:100568:3"/> and the pace to be creeping, and ſnaile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like: there is nothing in it that runs, but teares. Secondly, that it is <hi>an imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect work,</hi> and unfit for that end to which it ſeems to be deſigned; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I gladly would that it might have been ſtill hid like <hi>Saul</hi> behind the ſtuffe, and not have appeared in publick view. For I know it will be looked upon as a kind of record that beares upon it the name of the <hi>Lady HONOR VYNER,</hi> whoſe name ſhould alwaies be written by me, <hi>aureis potius literis, quam vili hoc liquore,</hi> in Letters of Gold rather then with this vile and cheap Inke, ſo many were my obligations to her for the conſtant and reall favours that ſhe was pleaſed to heap upon me, which muſt ſtill live, and be acknowliged by me: But the beſt at preſent that I can make of this way is, that black is ſuitable to mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
<pb facs="tcp:100568:3"/> and that broken notes, ſentences, and inconſiſtencies (with which I feare this little piece abounds) are in ſorrow pardonable, if not commendable. And this is all that I ſhall now ſay on my own behalf.</p>
            <p>To you Sir, who are ſtill a ſad mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner under this band and ſtroke of God, I hope this Sermon may afford ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing conſiderations as may cauſe you not to ſorrow as others that have no hopes, in regard that ſhe is not <hi>dead</hi> but <hi>ſleeps,</hi> is not <hi>loſt</hi> but <hi>found,</hi> not taken from the company of the <hi>living,</hi> but of the <hi>lamenting.</hi> Though therefore your eyes may drop as a <hi>limbeck,</hi> yet let them not run as <hi>ſpouts;</hi> though ſighs may come from you, yet take heed of <hi>repi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings.</hi> It is God that hath done it, and who ſhall ſay unto him, What doſt thou? I know you do ſtrive againſt dejections,
<pb facs="tcp:100568:4"/> (and I bleſſe God) that hitherto you have born your croſſe as becomes a Chriſtian; continue, I beſeech you ſtill in the exerciſe of Faith and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, that ſo when you are tried, you may receive the Crown of life that the Lord hath promiſed to thoſe that love him, <hi>James 1. 12.</hi> And that you may thus do, and be thus crowned, ſhall be the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of him, who thankefully acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all your love, and reſts</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt affectionate friend and ſervant in the Lord WILLIAM SPURSTOWE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100568:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>DEATH and the GRAVE no Bar to a BELIEVERS Happineſs.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSAL. 17. 15.</bibl>
               <q>I ſhall be ſatisfied, when I awake with thy likeneſs.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>t is ſtoried by the famous <hi>Tully</hi> concerning <hi>Syracuſe,</hi> that there is no day throughout the whole yeer ſo ſtormy, and tempeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, in which the inhabitants have not ſome glimpſe and ſight of the Sunne: The like obſervation may be truly made on all thoſe Pſalms of <hi>David,</hi> in which his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints are moſt multiplied, his feares, and preſſures moſt inſiſted on, that there is
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100568:5"/> not any of them ſo totally overcaſt with the black darkneſs of deſpaire; but that we may eaſily diſcern them to be here and there interveined and ſtreaked with ſome comfortable expreſſions of his faith and hope in God. If in the beginning of a Pſalm we finde him reſtleſs in his motions, like <hi>Noahs</hi> Dove upon the overſpreading waters; yet in the cloſe we ſhall ſee him like the ſame Dove returning with an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live branch in its mouth, and fixing upon the Ark. If we finde him in another Pſalm ſtaggering in the midſt of his diſtreſſes through the prevalency of carnall feares; we may alſo in it behold him recovering himſelf again, by fetching arguments from faith, whoſe <hi>topicks</hi> are of an higher ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation then to be ſhaken by the timerous ſuggeſtions that ariſe from the fleſh. If at another time we behold him like to a boat on drift, that is toſſed and beaten by the inconſtant winds, and fierce waves, yet we ſhall ſtill finde all his rollings and agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be ſuch as carry him towards the ſtanding ſhore, where he rides at laſt both in peace and ſafety. And of all this the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100568:5"/> preſent Pſalm is both a full and lively in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
            <p>For in it holy <hi>Davids</hi> afflictions are neither few nor ſmall: His <hi>innocency</hi> that is wounded by malicious ſlanders, His <hi>life</hi> that is in jeopardy by deadly enemies that compaſs him about, His <hi>preſent condition</hi> that is imbittered unto him by the preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing wants of a barren Wilderneſs, while his foes live deliciouſly in <hi>Sauls</hi> Court. And yet under the weight and combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſo many ſore evils, <hi>David</hi> carries himſelfe as one that is neither hopeleſs nor forſaken: yea, layes his eſtate in the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance againſt theirs, and in this low ebbe of his vies with them for happineſſe; and at laſt ſhutting up the Pſalm with a trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant <hi>Epiphonema,</hi> concludes himſelfe to be by far the better man. <hi>As for me, I ſhall behold thy face in righteouſneſſe, I ſhall be ſatisfied when I awake with thy likeneſſe.</hi> They 'tis true enjoy the face of their King, whoſe favour is as a cloud of latter rain promiſing a fruitfull harveſt of many bleſſings, <hi>But I</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall behold the face of God in right<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouſneſſe;</hi> whoſe loving:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100568:6"/> kindneſſe is better then life, cloathed with all its Royalties: they have their bellies filled with hidden treaſure, having more then a common hand of bounty opened unto them; but I have more gladneſs put into my heart, more then in the time that their Corn and Wine encre<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſed. They have their portion in hand, as being men of this world; but I have mine laid up in the other: <hi>I ſhall be ſatisfied when I awake with thy likeneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the words we have his and every be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers eternall happineſs in the other life, ſet forth in three particulars as a moſt effectuall Antidote againſt preſent trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and temptations that ariſe from the malice of wicked men againſtt them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the time of his abſolute and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat happineſs. <hi>Cum evigilavero, when I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake.</hi> Some Interpreters conceive, that by this waking the Prophet intends no more then to expreſſe the lively ſence and confidence that he hath of the return of Gods favour unto him, under this dark night of trouble and ſorrow which is now upon him: and though he now be like
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100568:6"/> thoſe that are aſleep, who for that time want thoſe pleaſures and delights which others enjoy; yet he ſhall awake again to behold the light of Gods face ſhining up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him like a bright Sunne with manifold emanations of love and bounty. But o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers both of the Ancient and Modern carry the Metaphor far higher, applying it to the reſurrection, and the ſtate of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs after death, which to me ſeems to be both a full and genuine interpretation; in regard that <hi>David</hi> comforteth himſelfe in his preſent wants with the hopes of an after happineſs, totally differenced from that which thoſe whom he ſtiles <hi>the men of the World,</hi> and ſuch as have <hi>their portion in this life</hi> are made partakers of.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is the <hi>meaſure</hi> and redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dancy of his happineſs: <hi>I ſhall be ſatisfied.</hi> The Sun is not ſo full of light, nor the Sea of water, as he ſhall be at his awaking of endleſs bliſs and perfection. Our deſires in this life are (as the Lawyers ſay, of ones will while he lives) wholy <hi>ambulatory,</hi> and admit of as many alterations, as ſuch teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments doe of additions and expunctions;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100568:7"/> being neither <hi>filled</hi> nor <hi>fixed</hi> with the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any ſatisfactory good: But in the the other life our deſires are terminated in the fulneſs of our enjoyments, and as <hi>faith</hi> is ſwallowed up in <hi>viſion,</hi> ſo are our <hi>deſires</hi> in <hi>complacency:</hi> we affect nothing that we have not, and we have nothing that we do not affect.</p>
            <p>The third is the <hi>object</hi> of his happineſs, together with the <hi>manner</hi> of his enjoying it <hi>: I ſhall be ſatisfied with thy likeneſſe.</hi> The <hi>object</hi> is the <hi>likeneſſe</hi> of God, that is, his glory and perfection, with which he ſits clothed on his Throne of Majeſty. The <hi>manner</hi> of enjoying it, is by beholding of it; not by way of reſultancy, and <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ante ſpeculo,</hi> by the conveyance and help of a glaſs; but by an immediate, clear, and permanent viſion, in which he ſhall be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the knowledge and ſight of God, ſo farre as the capacity of a creature can reach unto: but as it is impoſſible to bring the vaſt body of the Sunne into the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row compaſſe of the eye that beholds it; ſo is it much more impoſſible to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the being of an infinite God within the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100568:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> limits of a finite underſtanding, when ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated and widened to its higheſt pitch.</p>
            <p>Having opened the words in the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall branches, which naturally they ſhoot forth into: I ſhall begin with the firſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, the time of <hi>Davids</hi> and every be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers compleat happineſſe: [<hi>When I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake</hi>] And from it gather two Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>The firſt, (which I ſhall but briefly touch) is, <hi>That death to the godly is no more then a ſleep.</hi> The grave in which they reſt is as their bed; the darkneſs of it as the night; and their reſurrection from it, as the joyfull morning. The Heathens have called death by the name of ſleep as well as the Scripture. <hi>Homer</hi> ſaith, that ſleep and death have one mother, and are begotten of the night: And the <hi>Cynick</hi> falling into a ſleep, a little before his death, pleaſantly ſaid, <hi>Frater me mox traditurus eſt fratri ſuo;</hi> one brother is now delivering me into the hands of another: but yet they never ſtiled it ſo upon the ſame ground which the Scripture doth, neither ever could, being wholy ignorant of Chriſt, by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100568:8"/> whom death is wonderfully changed from an enemy to a friend, from a curſe to a bleſſing, and is put into the Inventory of the Saints priviledges which accrew unto them by Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 22. It comes now to them rather <hi>by ſin, then for ſin,</hi> becauſe it is not <hi>in ordine a peccato ad ſupplicium, ſed ad ſalutem:</hi> it comes not as a middle thing between <hi>ſin and damnation,</hi> but <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſin and ſalvation.</hi> And therefore may now fitly be reſembled to a ſleep in theſe reſpects.</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſleep is a <hi>ligation,</hi> not an <hi>abla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the externall ſenſes; it obſtructs their function and exerciſe, but it doth not deſtroy the faculty: So death inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts and ſuſpends the action of life, but it doth not extinguiſh the root and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of a believers life, ſo as to make it to admit of no return. The Philoſopher thought indeed the diſſolution of the body to be argument full enough to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the impoſſibility of its reſurrection, and therefore derided the doctrine of it when <hi>Paul</hi> preached it, <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 18. But <hi>Job</hi> tells us, that though his reines be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100568:8"/> within him, that yet with his eyes he ſhould behold God, <hi>Job</hi> 19. 27. and the Prophet ſaith, that Chriſts dead ſhall ariſe and ſing, <hi>Jſay</hi> 26. 19. The ſilence of the grave is but a kind of <hi>Pythagorian</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or reſtraint onely for a time; ſight, hearing, ſpeech ſhall all return again. For though death hath made a ſeparation between ſoul and body, yet neither ſoul nor body are by it ſeparated from Chriſt: but as in <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Union <hi>Hypoſtatical;</hi> ſo in his <hi>members</hi> the Union <hi>myſtical</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable: and therfore they are ſaid <hi>to ſleep in Jeſus, 1 Theſ:</hi> 4. 14. to <hi>die</hi> not <hi>out</hi> of the Lord but <hi>in the Lord, Rev.</hi> 14. 13. yea <hi>into the Lord, Rom.</hi> 14. 8. ſo as by death to be more cloſely joyned to him: being then united to him that lives for evermore, their very duſt muſt needs be a living part of him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in regard both of the time and manner of ſleep and death. Some as children are put ſooner to bed; others a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain ſit up longer before they go to ſleep: ſome have their life like a Winter day ſhort and cloudy, and with them it is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100568:9"/> quickly night; ſome have it lengthned out like to a Summer day, and with them it is late before the evening of their life ſhuts in. Some as children when undreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by their Parents, begin to ſtruggle and expreſs a backwardneſs; others again as throughly wearied with their ſtirring, call to be had to bed: And ſo ſome Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſhrink at the approaches of death, and are loth to be unclothed; others a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain as burthened with their earthly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, groan to have mortality to be ſwallowed up of life. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> when the Prophet bids him ſet his houſe in order, for he muſt die and not live, turned his face to the wall and wept ſore, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 20. 3. But <hi>Paul</hi> he deſires to be diſſolved and to be with Chriſt, which is beſt of all, <hi>Philip.</hi> 1. 21.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, death is a ſleep in regard of the likeneſs of our being awakened both from the one and from the other. It is obſerved by the Naturaliſts that no noiſe more ſuddenly awaketh a man from his ſleep, then an Humane voice; yea though it be that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that heavie and deep
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100568:9"/> ſlumber which precedeth death it ſelf, as the Aphoriſme noteth it in <hi>Hippocrates.</hi> The way by which our Saviour raiſed <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus, John</hi> 11. 45. and <hi>Peter</hi> raiſed <hi>Tabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha,</hi> was by a voice, <hi>Acts</hi> 9. 40. And the way by which all the congregation of the dead ſhall be awakened from the grave, ſhall be, not by the immediate voice of God, but by the voice of the <hi>Son of man. The hour commeth</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>in which all that are in the grave ſhall hear his voice and come forth, John</hi> 5. 28. It is his voice that ſhall cauſe the Sea to give up its dead, and ſhall make the bones of his Saints that are ſcattered over the face of the whole earth to come together.</p>
            <p>But it is not my purpoſe to weary the Metaphor in a full and cloſe purſuit of it, or to draw an exact parallel between ſleep and death: It being a point that I leaſt aimed at in this preſent exerciſe. The application that I ſhall make is briefly double.</p>
            <p>Firſt, if death be but a ſleep to belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, then it ſhould cauſe us to moderate our ſorrow on the behalf of our deareſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100568:10"/> friends and relations that are fallen aſleep in the Lord: as alſo to correct that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of fear in regard of our ſelves, who are apt to be diſmayed at the harbingers of the King of terrors, <hi>age, pain,</hi> and <hi>ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and to ſink under the ſad thoughts of an imminent diſſolution. Who is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled when he underſtands his ſick friend is laid down to reſt? and who is afraid to put off his clothes at night, when he goes to bed? Sleep is not an <hi>hurtfull,</hi> but a <hi>neceſſary</hi> kind of privation and intermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: It is the ſick mans Phyſitian, the travellers and labouring mans reſtorative, the only <hi>Parentheſis</hi> of the afflicted mans ſorrows; and from hence it is that <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> in his <hi>Ethicks</hi> ſaith, that for well nigh half their time the miſerable and the happy do little differ. And are not all theſe together with far more high advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages found to meet in the believers ſleep of death? is there not then a perfect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe from all the miſeries of this life? is there not by it a cure wrought of all the maladies both of the ſoule and of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſo that the one ſhall no more relapſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100568:10"/> into its former ſins, nor the other into its old diſeaſes &amp; cares? the eye ſhal not weep for ſorrow, nor the brow ſweat with labor, the head ſhall not ake with the multitude of anxious thoughts, nor the phancy be moleſted with the dreams &amp; viſions of the night: when we awake from it we ſhall ſay it was the beſt and quieteſt ſleep that ever we ſlept, and the beſt phyſick that ever we took for the putting of a final pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod to all our diſtempers. Let not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore believers dread the thoughts of death as others doe, nor ſhreek out when they eſpie this ſnake creeping into their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms; for hurt them it cannot having loſt its ſting; but benefit them it ſhall, being made by Chriſt an egreſs from all miſery, and an ingreſs into all happineſs.</p>
            <p>The ſecond application is, to acquaint us how neceſſary it is to exerciſe faith and holineſs while we live, that death may be a comfortable ſleep to us when we die. No man can die in the Lord that lives not to the Lord; nor ſhall awake from death to happineſſe, that doth not firſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake from ſin to holineſs. It is a vain
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100568:11"/> preſumption to conceive that a man that lives and dies in his ſins, can ever have the ſame joyful reſurrection with them that have made it their conſtant work to die to their ſin. Northern and Southern ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers though they run from contrary points meet in the ſame Sea; but they whoſe waies and Principles are contrary unto theirs that profeſs holineſs, ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be found with them in the ſame Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. If we look for according to Gods promiſe, new heavens and a new earth wherein dwelleth righteouſneſs, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 13. we muſt have righteouſneſs dwelling in us here, or elſe we ſhall never dwell in them hereafter. O then that they would lay this to heart who dread the ſeparation of the ſoul from the body; but yet are not at all afraid of the ſeparation and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union both of the body and ſoul from God, that ſo they may timely buſie themſelves in thoſe waies and duties, which may make the firſt death that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly be avoided by them, to be comfortable to them; and may alſo who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prevent their dying of the ſecond
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100568:11"/> death, which leaves all thoſe that fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſtroke of it eternally hopeleſs.</p>
            <p>And thus I have done with the firſt Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, touching it well nigh with as light an hand as <hi>Jonathan</hi> did the honey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb, into which he onely dipt the end of his rod; but by that ſmall taſt his eyes were enlightned; and ſo I hope may ours alſo by that little which hath been ſpoken of it. There remains yet a ſecond obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which growes as ripe fruit upon the ſame branch and is next to be gathered, and that is this.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> That the happineſs of believers is not abſolute and entire untill their reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from the grave: nor are they filled with bliſs and glory to ſatisfaction till they be awaked. In nature the tree puts forth firſt buds, then bloſſoms, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by a further digeſtion of the ſap there is a production of the fruit: and ſo it is with believers in their ſupernatural and eternal bleſſedneſs, in which they are not at once eſtated; but have it firſt in the buddings of it by faith and hope, in the blooming of it by the joyes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100568:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the Spirit, with which they are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten lifted up towards Heaven; but the ultimate fulneſs of it, they enjoy not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the whole man come to be poſſeſſed of Heaven. <hi>We are now the ſons of God, but it doth not yet app<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar what we ſhall be, 1 John</hi> 2. 2. Our preſent condition at beſt falls as far ſhort of our future, as a faint ray doth of the Sun when it ſhines in its full ſtrength. The learned <hi>Verulams</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of Prophecies falls in much with the manner of our celeſtial happineſs, who ſaith, that they have <hi>gradus &amp; ſcalas com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plementi,</hi> certain gradual fulfillings, in each of which they grow more clear and diſtinct: And ſo hath it ſundrie progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive ſteps, and aſcentions, in each of which we are truly partakers of it after a gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing and encreaſing way, as I ſhall ſhow in five ſteps.</p>
            <p>Firſt, believers have life and eternal bleſſedneſs, <hi>in pretio,</hi> in the price that is laid down for it. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 14. It is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a <hi>purchaſed poſſeſſion,</hi> an inheritance that doth not deſcend to us by <hi>birth;</hi> but is given to us by <hi>grace.</hi> He who hath a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100568:12"/> 
               <hi>natural</hi> right unto it, as being the <hi>heir of all things, Heb.</hi> 1. 2. hath given unto us a right of <hi>purchaſe:</hi> Our title is founded in Chriſts bloud which makes it truly ours; he having by it obtained a power to give eternal life to whomſoever he pleaſeth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, believers have it <hi>in promiſſo,</hi> in the promiſe, which is a declaration and conveyance of what Chriſt hath purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be to their behoof, and the oath of God which is added to it, is as the ſeal upon the label of the deed, that gives a further ratification unto it; that ſo by <hi>two immutable things in which it was impoſſible for God to lie, they might have ſtrong con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, Heb.</hi> 6. 18. And who is it that by the eye of faith views and reads thoſe evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, in which a crown of life, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2. 10. a Kingdome that cannot be moved, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 28. an inheritance that fadeth not away, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 4. are all aſcertained to him, doth not rejoyce more under the hopes of glory, then the greateſt of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ever can in the fruition of all their worldly greatneſſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they are partakers of Heaven
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100568:13"/> it ſelfe, <hi>in prodromo,</hi> in their fore-runner, the Lord Chriſt. He at his aſcenſion took ſeiſin and livery of it in their name, <hi>John 14. 2. I goe to prepare a place for you.</hi> An expreſſion (as ſome conceive) borrowed from travellers, amongſt whom ſome one is by agreement ſent before to take up lodgings for the reſt of his company. And as he takes, ſo alſo doth he keepe poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in their names, preſerving ſtill their right unto it, untill they come to be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of it themſelves. And hence it is, that the Apoſtle ſaith of believers, that <hi>they are raiſed up together, and made to ſit together in heavenly places in Chriſt,</hi> Epheſ. 2. 6.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, they have the happineſſe of Heaven, <hi>in primitiis,</hi> in the firſt-fruits, and pledges of it, every grace of the Spirit is <hi>ſcintilla futurae lucis,</hi> a ſparke of their future glory; every comfort of it is <hi>gutta font is vitae,</hi> a drop of the well of life; and are as certain evidences of an enſuing ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; as the day-ſtar is of an approaching morning. The taſts and prelibations of happineſſe, which believers have in this
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100568:13"/> life by the mouth of faith, the ſight of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven which they have by the eye of faith, that ſometimes ſtands, on tiptoe, and peeps into the things that are within the vaile, doe differ onely in degree and not in kind from the full ſruition and viſion of God which they have in the other life, when their ſouls and bodie, are reunited to each other, and both con<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oyned unto Chriſt their everliving head and Lord.</p>
            <p>Fifthly and laftly, believers have life and eternall bleſſedneſſe, <hi>in meſſe,</hi> in the rich and full harveſt of it; when all the promiſes both of grace and glory are wholy accompliſhed, when all the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations of faith and hope are ſwallowed up in endleſſe admiration, when all the deſires of the ſoule, which are more reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe then the Sunne in their motions, are eternally fixed upon one ſimple and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite good, which contains in it the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of all delectible objects. <hi>Quid <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o avarius cui Deus non ſufficit in quo ſunt omnia?</hi> What can be more inſatiable then that man, whom God doth not ſuffice in whom all things are? can any thirſt after
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100568:14"/> a larger poſſeſſion then immenſity? a ſurer ſtate then immortality? a longer term of yeers then perpetuity?</p>
            <p>But if you ask me why God defers the conſummation of his childrens happineſſe unto the reſurrection, and makes it to be like a <hi>Jacobs</hi> ladder, that hath ſundry ſteps and aſcenſions: amongſt many grounds that may be aſſigned, be pleaſed to take theſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, God doth it that he may hide his counſels and purpoſes concerning his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren from the eyes and knowledg of carnal &amp; proud men, to whom the external mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt and his followers becomes a ſtumbling-block, and a juſt occaſion to make them periſh in their ſins. And he doth it alſo that he may hide his people from their rage and fury, who are as impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient at the leaſt appearances of their wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, as Bulls are at the fight of Scarlet. They envy them their morſels of bread, much more their Manna; their rags, much more their robes. The evil husbandmen in the Goſpel as ſoon as they beheld the heir, deale worſe with him then with their
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100568:14"/> Lords ſervants, <hi>Luke</hi> 20. 14. And did but the wicked of the world but fully know whoſe the inheritance of Heaven were, they would fall upon them as the Jewes upon <hi>Steven,</hi> and ſtone them to death.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God doth it that he may ſhew forth the greatneſs of his power. Alchy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts boaſt much of their skill, that they can turn baſer mettalls into more noble, Lead into Silver, Copper into gold, but the ground upon which they build their preſumption is, that theſe baſer mettals are in their nature in the way to be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and ſo they doe but perfect that which is imperfect and would by courſe of nature have become perfect though they had never laboured it; But they never aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayed to turn droſs into Silver, or dirt into Gold. And yet the power which God putteth forth is far greater, when he rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his children from the grave to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and makes them that were <hi>Netherlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> dwelling in the duſt, to be citizens of the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> which is above, the companions of Angels, and coheirs with Chriſt. Who but an infinite power can
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100568:15"/> make a vile corruptible body to put on incorruption? or can change a naturall body into a ſpirituall body, ſo as that it ſhall not need the aſſiſtance of meats and drinks, but live as the Angels doe? or can make a body ſowne in diſhonour to riſe in honour, being beautified with the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious endowments of <hi>clarity, agility,</hi> and <hi>impaſſibility?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, God defers the full happineſs of believers till their reſurrection, that they may have occaſion to ſhew forth and exerciſe all kind of graces that bring glory and honour to himſelfe. If the crown were ſet upon their heads, while they were as infants in the cradle, where would their patience in enduring trials and in waiting on the pleaſure of God be made viſible to the world? If they were all forthwith ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up from earth to heaven, where would be the exerciſe of their hope, and earneſt longing after the appearing of Chriſt in glory? If there were no ſuch changes as death and diſſolution intervening, where would be the glory of the Chriſtians faith who now believe that which the line of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100568:15"/> reaſon cannot fathome. Is there any deſart ſo hopeleſſe as death and the grave, deſertion of life and being, when <hi>milke</hi> forſakes the <hi>breſts, marrow</hi> the <hi>bones, bloud</hi> the <hi>veines, ſpirit</hi> the <hi>arteries;</hi> and the <hi>ſoule</hi> the <hi>body?</hi> And yet after ſuch deſolations faith expects a reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <hi>I know</hi> (ſaith <hi>Job) that my Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer liveth, and that he ſhall ſtand upon the Earth at the latter day: and though after my skin worms deſtroy this body, yet in my fleſh ſhall I ſee God, Job</hi> 19. 25, 26. Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers know the power of God can eaſily break aſunder the bands of death, and therefore yield to it as priſoners of hope.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, God doth it, that there may be a conformity between Chriſts and the believers entrance into glory. He was firſt abaſed, and then exalted; He ſuffered, and then was crowned; he deſcended into the grave, and then aſcended into Heaven. <hi>O fooles and ſlow of heart to believe all that the Prophets have ſpoken; ought not Chriſt to have ſuffered theſe things, and to enter into his glory?</hi> ſaith our Saviour to his doubting Diſciples, <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 25, 26. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100568:16"/> if He went from the Croſſe to his Throne, it is not meet that we ſhould <hi>balk</hi> the one, and <hi>take</hi> the other: If he were ſtripped naked, before he was cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with Majeſty and honour, we may not refuſe to undergoe the ſame condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with him; eſpecially he having ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified to us <hi>abaſements, afflictions, death</hi> and the <hi>grave,</hi> by undergoing them for us.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, God doth it, that he may declare himſelf <hi>juſt</hi> in his <hi>threatnings,</hi> as well as <hi>gracious</hi> in his <hi>promiſes.</hi> It was his Law that if any man did offend, he ſhould die the death; and therefore though he hath taken away the curſe from off the ſoul, yet he hath not taken away the ſtroke of it from the body; though he have in mercy freed his choſen ones from Hell, yet he hath not exempted them from the grave. Let not therefore any ſo <hi>preſume</hi> on his <hi>goodneſs,</hi> as to <hi>ſlight</hi> his <hi>juſtice,</hi> or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that the <hi>promiſes</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell</hi> have vacated the <hi>threatnings</hi> of the <hi>Law:</hi> but let them remember, that he is known by executing of judgement, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9. 16.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100568:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> as well as by ſhewing mercy, <hi>Exodus</hi> 34. 7.</p>
            <p>In the application of this truth I ſhall be very brief, and touch onely upon two in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, without inſiſting upon either, that ſo I may not by the lapſe of time be wholy fruſtrated in ſpeaking to other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, that are yet like rich hangings fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded up and not preſented to our view.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it may acquaint us how needful a grace patience is to believers, whoſe feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city is in expectation, not in poſſeſſion, whoſe life is a ſeeds-time, and not an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, that ſo they may not droop at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay of the promiſe. It is one choice piece of the ſpiritual armour with which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle would have the <hi>Epheſians</hi> feet to be ſhod, to ſecure them both againſt the roughneſs, and the length of their way, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. 15. It is that he prayes for in the behalf of the <hi>Theſſalonians, that God would direct their hearts into the patient waiting for Chriſt, 2 Theſ.</hi> 3. 5. It is the commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation oſ the Saints given by the Angel, <hi>Revel.</hi> 14. 12. that they bare patiently the furious aſſaults of Antichriſt without fainting, expecting by faith his ruine and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100568:17"/> their own exaltation. Let us therefore arme our ſelves with the ſame mind, both in running our race, and bearing our bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens without murmuring or dejection, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving that in the beſt ſeaſon God will make our happineſſe to grow as the light, untill it be conſummated in its ultimate perfection and ſtability.</p>
            <p>The ſecond inference is, that though the compleat happineſſe of believers be fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that yet it is no ground to any to ſlacken their preſent diligence of <hi>ſtanding perfect and compleat in all the will of God, Col.</hi> 4. 12. or to procraſtinate their ſervice till they draw neerer the borders of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World, becauſe they conceive the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to ſtand at a great diſtance: for when they have done whatever we can imagine to lye within the latitude of a creatures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, yet their work will never ariſe to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny equality with their wages. For could we ſuppoſe a mans obedience from his birth to run in a paralell line with the <hi>purity</hi> of the whole law, and that he ſhould abide in that eſtate as many yeers as the world hath ſtood minuits; yet when the total ſumme
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100568:17"/> of all his duties and ſervices is caſt up, it would fall as far ſhort of the reward with which God crowns the ſervices of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as the ſmalleſt fraction doth of the greateſt number, or the leaſt filing of gold of the riches of the whole Indies. How ſedulous and careful therefore ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers be, to let ſlip no ſeaſon, nor to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlow any occaſion of honouring God in the exerciſe of all holineſſe, whoſe time is but ſhort, whoſe works are but imperfect; and yet are rewarded with full and endleſs bliſſe.</p>
            <p>I leave now the firſt particular the <hi>time</hi> of <hi>Davids</hi> happineſs [<hi>when I awake</hi>] and come to the ſecond, the <hi>meaſure</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundancy of it, which follows next as well in order of the words, as of the parts: <hi>When I wake I ſhall be ſatisfied.</hi> This one word <hi>ſatiabor,</hi> points out the wide diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence that is between Earth and Heaven; the one is the place of <hi>deſires,</hi> and they ſpeak <hi>indigency,</hi> the other of <hi>having,</hi> and that ſpeaks <hi>fulneſs.</hi> Whom <hi>have I in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven but thee O Lord? And there is none up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth that I deſire beſides thee, Pſal.</hi> 73.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100568:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> 25. On Earth we may have <hi>contentment,</hi> which conſiſts in curbing our appetite, and bringing our mind to our eſtate, but in Heaven we have <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> and that is, when our eſtate is fully according to our mind and deſires. Then all the thirſty ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites of the ſoul, and of the whole man are filled and ſatisfied with enjoyments ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the ſeveral faculties: The under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that is filled to its utmoſt capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city with truth, the will that is ſatisfied with goodneſſe, and the ſenſes with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. When therefore believers change Earth for Heaven they doe not loſe their happineſſe but perfect it: as Fiſh when they fall out of the narrow and ſmall brooks into the wide and deep Sea do not leave their Element, but are more in it then before.</p>
            <p>To open more diſtinctly the fulneſs and perfection of the bleſſedneſſe of Heaven, I ſhall ſet it forth two waies. Firſt, <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Poſitively.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, let us compare it to the beſt things here below, ſuch as mens hearts, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours are moſt carried forth unto, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100568:18"/> we ſhall quickly find how light they will be in the ballance, and how heavy the other. Gold, pearls, precious ſtones do <hi>but</hi> ſerve to ſet forth the pavements of the ſtreets, the Walls and Gates of the <hi>new Jeruſalem, Revel.</hi> 31. But alas! they are too mean things to ſhadow forth rhe riches, glory and dignity of the Inhabitants? What is the beauty of the High Prieſt garments wherewith he entred into the Holy of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, to thoſe robes of righteouſneſſe with which the Saints are cloathed? What is <hi>Solomons</hi> throne with its ſteps and aſcents, to the throne upon which they ſit? What are his ſervants and attendants, which aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the Queen of <hi>Sheba,</hi> to thoſe Angels that are their miniſtring ſpirits? they are but as rags, as a dunghil, as motes in the Sun-beam to the beam it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Secondly, compare it with the ſoreſt ſufferings and afflictions that any have, or may ſuſtain while they are in the body, and they will all be as ſo many foiles to ſet off the pefection of the happineſſe of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens Who have met with harder meaſure from the World by perſecutions, by tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100568:19"/> by ſlaughters, then Chriſtians? and who have ſuſtained them with ſuch cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and reſolution as they have done? giving greater thanks to their enemies, when they have been condemned, then when abſolved. <hi>Paul</hi> under the hope of glory, joyes in tribulation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 3. The believing Hebrews knowing that they have in Heaven an enduring ſubſtance, take joyfully the ſpoyling of their goods, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 34. Others that they might obtain a better reſurrection, have not accepted of deliverance from the ſword, flames and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tortures when it hath been offered unto them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11, 35. It is ſtoried of <hi>Adrianus</hi> that Martyr, that ſeeing many Chriſtians put to ſo cruel and bitter deaths, he asked others of them what it was that they ſuffered ſuch grievous things for; and their Anſwer was, <hi>Speramus illa bona quae oculus non vidit, auris non audivit, in cor hominis non aſcenderunt:</hi> We hope for thoſe things which eye hath not ſeen, ear hath not heard, nor ever entred into the heart of man to conceive. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he was ſo moved, that he forthwith
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100568:19"/> deſired to be enrolled in the catalogue of Martyrs, and ſo ſuffered his Wife exciting him thereunto. Needs therefore muſt the happineſſe of Heaven be full and perfect, when for it, men are willing to <hi>forgoe</hi> the <hi>ſweeteſt</hi> things, and to <hi>undergoe</hi> the <hi>har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt;</hi> and yet reckon all <hi>not worthy of the Glory that ſhall be revealed in them, Rom.</hi> 8. 18.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the fulneſſe of the felicity of Heaven may appear, if we compare it with the <hi>joyes and comforts of the Holy Spirit.</hi> Such they are, as that the Scripture ſtyles them <hi>ſtrong conſolations, Heb. 6. 17. full joyes, John 15. 11. Joy unſpeakable</hi> and <hi>full of Glory, 1 Pet. 1. 8. abounding con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations, 2 Cor.</hi> 1. 5. And yet all the joy and peace that believers are partakers of in this life is but as a drop to the Ocean, as a ſingle cluſter to the whole Vintage, as the Thyme or Honey upon the thigh of a Bee to the whole Hive fully fraught with it, or as the break and peep of day to the bright no<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n-tide. But yet theſe taſts of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Wine, and Honey of this celeſtial <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> with which the Holy Spirit makes
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100568:20"/> glad the hearts of believers are both far more deſirable and ſatisfactory then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verflowing ſtreams of all earthly felicities: And there are none who have once taſted of them, but ſay as the <hi>Samaritan</hi> woman did, <hi>Lord give me that Water that I thirſt not, neither come hither to draw, John</hi> 4. 15. So alſo the firſt and early dawnings of the heavenly light fill the ſoul with more ſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and raviſh it with more pure joy, then the brighteſt Sun-ſhine of all worldly ſplendor can ever doe. I have read of a devout Perſon who but dreaming of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the ſignatures and impreſſions it made upon his fancy were ſo ſtrong, as that when he awaked he knew not his Cell, could not diſtinguiſh the night from the day, nor difference by his taſte Oyle from Wine, ſtill he was calling for his viſion and ſaying, <hi>Redde mihi campos floridos, colum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam anream, comitem Hieronymum, aſſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Angelos.</hi> Give me my freſh and fragrant fields againe, my Golden pillar of light, <hi>Jerom</hi> my companion, Angels my aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants. If Heaven in a dream produce ſuch extacies, as drown and overwhelm the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100568:20"/> exerciſe of the ſenſes to inferiour objects; what tranſes and complacencies muſt the fruition of it work in thoſe, who have their whole rational appetite filled, and their body beautified with its endleſſe glory?</p>
            <p>Secondly, as we have ſeen the tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent fulneſſe of Heavens happineſs <hi>compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively;</hi> ſo now let us view it a little <hi>poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively,</hi> and that both in its <hi>cauſes</hi> and in its <hi>properties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, the <hi>efficient cauſe</hi> of all the fulneſs and glory of Heaven is God. It is his royal manſion built by himſelf, and for himſelf, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 10. No Artiſt had either head or hand in the creating of this ſtately fabrick; for who could make it ſutable to his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs but himſelfe, who onely underſtands his own excellency. The Tabernacle, the Temple in which his typical preſence only was, were both by his appointment to have art and coſt beſtowed upon them, that ſo they might the better draw reſpect and reverence to his name who was wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped in them: how much more will God beautifie and deck his Throne of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100568:21"/> on which he ſits, &amp; on which he will manifeſt himſelf in all perfection unto the whole Aſſembly of the firſt born, whoſe names are written in Heaven, that he may forever be adored, and admired by them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if we look upon Heaven in the <hi>meritorious cauſe</hi> of it, as it is a purchaſed inheritance; ſo it will appear alſo to be full of glory. When we hear what a vaſt ſum hath been given for a Lordſhip, for a Jewel or Diamond by them that have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>propreiators</hi> of them, we uſually conclude, that they are of more then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon worth, or elſe men would not have expended ſo much treaſure for them: How much better may we argue, the worth and excellency of Heaven, for which the Lord Chriſt laid down his bloud as a price to gain us thereby a right and a title unto it. Surely he who is the wiſdom of God knew the value and worth of it to be ſuch as none but himſelf could ever have been able to compaſs, or elſe he would not have given his precious bloud for that, for which men or Angels had been ſufficient to have bought with their ſtock.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:100568:21"/>
            <p>Thirdly, the riches and glory of Heaven is ſeen in this, that Chriſt is the <hi>exemplary cauſe,</hi> and pattern to whom believers are to be conformed. <hi>He ſhall change our vile body</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that it may be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioned like to his glorious body, Phil.</hi> 3. 21. In his abaſement he became like us bearing upon him our infirmities; but in our exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation we ſhall be made like unto him: We ſhall not onely behold his glory; but we ſhall be partakers of it. And can they want any thing who ſit upon the <hi>ſame throne,</hi> who feed at the <hi>ſame table,</hi> who are cloathed with the <hi>robe</hi> of <hi>his righteouſneſs,</hi> who are dignified with the <hi>titles</hi> of being <hi>heirs</hi> with him, <hi>brethren to him,</hi> and <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> of <hi>him</hi> who is <hi>the head</hi> that f<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lleth All in all, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 23.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the full bleſſedneſſe of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven may be demonſtrated from the <hi>matter</hi> or <hi>object</hi> of it; which being fully perfect muſt needs make the partakers of it fully bleſſed. Felicity conſiſts in an aggrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all good, if any thing be wanting, it cannot be abſolute and intire: And can we find any perfect coacervation of all the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:100568:22"/> ſcattered objects of good, but in God, who as he is in all things, ſo all things are in him after a more excellent manner then ever they were, or can be in themſelves: they never were without <hi>imperfection,</hi> and ſince the fall not without <hi>impurity;</hi> but in him they are <hi>perfect</hi> without defect, and <hi>pure</hi> without polution. When therefore God in Heaven, and not any confluence of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted good is the object and matter of belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers happineſs, muſt it not needs be <hi>full?</hi> Can he that inherits all things, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21. 7. want any thing? or can he who hath a full and conſtant communication of God himſelf not inherit all things?</p>
            <p>Fifthly, the <hi>final cauſe:</hi> For Gods making Heaven proves the happineſſe of it to be perfect. Gods end in all his works is his glory; for he that is the fountain of his own being, muſt neceſſarily be the end of his own actions: but yet the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his own glory, are not in all his works alike, the more or leſs he communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates himſelf to them, the more or leſs are they glorious. Now there are no where ſuch perfect communications of God as in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100568:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> Heaven. That is the place deſigned by God, where all the riches of mercy and of glory that <hi>eye hath not ſeen, eare hath not heard, nor the heart of man conceived,</hi> ſhall be all revealed in their full luſtre and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: there <hi>pardoning grace</hi> in the full diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of all debts that could never have been paid, ſhall be for ever admired; there <hi>ſanctifying grace</hi> which is now imperfect ſhall be compleated: there we ſhall know, as we are known, and love as we are loved; loving God not as we do here with a love of <hi>deſire,</hi> but with a love of <hi>friendſhip,</hi> being for ever united to him, and made fully happy and bleſſed by him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the full and ſatisfactory hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of Heaven will appear in the inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>properties</hi> and <hi>adjuncts</hi> of it; but through want of time I can onely point at them in a brief gloſs upon thoſe words of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Pet. 1. 4. An inheritance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible, undefiled, and that fadeth not away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, it is felicity which is <hi>incorruptible.</hi> There is nothing on earth which ſerves either for <hi>neceſſity,</hi> or for <hi>delight,</hi> for <hi>food</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:100568:23"/> or for <hi>ornament,</hi> but it hath in it <hi>a latent ſoed</hi> of mortality which in time prevailes againſt it, and corrupts the being and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of it. <hi>Bread</hi> that is the ſtaff of life, <hi>that</hi> in a few dayes moulds. And <hi>Manna</hi> that for its excellency is Angels meat, if kept but a little <hi>that</hi> ſtinks: <hi>Gold</hi> that ſerves for riches <hi>that</hi> ruſts, and <hi>clothes</hi> that are for ornament wear into rags. But in <hi>Heaven</hi> there is nothing but what is free from corruption. The <hi>food</hi> which the Saints live on is the <hi>tree</hi> of life, Revel. 22. 2. <hi>the crown</hi> which they wear is a <hi>crown of life,</hi> Revel. 2. 10. The <hi>riches</hi> which they poſſeſs, are <hi>durable riches,</hi> Prov. 8. 18.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is <hi>undefiled.</hi> As it is free from <hi>corruption within;</hi> ſo is it alſo from <hi>ſoil</hi> or any abaſement from <hi>without.</hi> Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows cares, fears, take away the luſtre of all earthly felicity, and make it become like a chryſtal glaſs blown upon by ſome impure breath that retaines little or nothing of its native brightneſs: But in Heaven all our enjoyments are <hi>pure,</hi> without the leaſt ſtain or ſpot of any evils that may caſt a dimneſs upon their beauty, there is no <hi>fear</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:100568:23"/> of loſing what we have, nor vexing <hi>care</hi> in keeping what we have; no <hi>ſorrow</hi> in grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for any thing that we want: What ever we there poſſeſs is made delightful to us by an <hi>holy ſecurity,</hi> and a <hi>perfect compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is felicity that <hi>fadeth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</hi> There is a double fading to which the moſt deſirable things on earth are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject: the one is, when the <hi>things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves recede</hi> from that beauty and verdure with which they ſometimes flouriſhed: the other is, when they <hi>fade in our eſteem and affection,</hi> ſo as to become leſs amiable to us, and leſs deſired by us. But to nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe is the happineſſe of Heaven <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>able, as it abides in the ſame luſtre and brightneſs, which had in the firſt moment that we entred into it, ſo have we alſo the ſame height of raviſhing joyes and delights after Millions of years fruition of it.</p>
            <p>The uſes of this point might be various; but I may not draw them out into number or length, I ſhall therefore confine my ſelf to a brief nomination of two.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:100568:24"/>
            <p>Firſt, If the happineſs of Heaven be full and ſatisfactory, it ſhould then take off the edge both of our deſires and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours in the eager perſuit of things that are below. <hi>Illi ſapiant terrena, qui promiſſa coeleſtia non habent.</hi> Let them ſavour earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things (ſaith <hi>Jerom</hi> to <hi>Celantia</hi>) who have no intereſt in Heavenly promiſes: And yet it is both ſtrange, and ſad to ſee how earthly the converſations of many are who profeſſe to have Heavenly expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, running after the empty pleaſures, and periſhing delights of the World with as much vehemency and ſtrife as the ſmall Fiſh do after a fly, or rotten Worm that ſwims upon the top of the Water who ſhall firſt catch it. But alas! how do ſuch men belye their hopes and give occaſion to the World to ſay, that what ever they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs of Heaven carries more of a deſign in it then a real truth, and that they drop and let fall ſuch notions, as <hi>Atalanta</hi> did her golden balls, to ſtop and impede the courſe of others that themſelves may gain and graſpe the more? Let me beſeech you therefore who have taken upon you the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:100568:24"/> name of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> to raiſe up your minds and ſoules towards Heaven, where <hi>your Treaſure, your Crown, your Saviour,</hi> and <hi>your God</hi> all are, that thereby you may vindicate Religion from that reproach which it lies under, and your ſelves of that ſinne of earthly-mindedneſſe, which like a root of bitterneſſe hath ſpread it ſelfe, to the defiling of many; ſo that I may truly ſay, that from the daies of <hi>John the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt untill now the Kingdom of Heaven never ſuffered leſſe violence, nor the World more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, how great is their folly who exchange a full and ſatisfactory happineſſe for empty and tranſient pleaſures? and how ſad will their end be, when dying in their ſinnes, evill and miſery ſhall come upon them in its perfection? What is it that heightens the bleſſed condition of thoſe that are in Heaven, but this, that their happineſſe is pure without mixture, and laſting without end? And is not this the aggravation of the ſinners eſtate in Hell, that it is ſheere wrath without the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:100568:25"/> leaſt allay of mercy, with which they are filled; and that it is abiding wrath, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt hope of end, with which they are tormented? There is not ſo much as a drop of water to a <hi>lake</hi> of fire, not a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of eaſe to an <hi>eternity</hi> of pain. All their ſhort pleaſures are turned into ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings that are eternity to the bottom; their mirth is changed into endleſſe ſighings, their tabrets and ſhaumes into everlaſting beatings, and hammerings upon the anvils of their breaſts, their ſhoutings into how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and their clapping of hands into a perpetuall gnaſhing of teeth. O that I might therefore by a timely expoſtulation with ſinners prevent that deſolation that elſe will certainly befall them! <hi>Why doe you lay out your money for that which is not bread?</hi> Why do you refuſe the free tender of that mercy, which hereafter at any rate you would gladly purchaſe? Is then a little eaſe worth a World? and are now the comforts of God worth leſſe then a few baſe luſts? Would you then ſubſcribe to the hardeſt conditions of duty and ſet vice
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:100568:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> that God could propound, and ſay Yes Lord to every queſtion? and will you now make a deniall to every woing? <hi>O conſider this all ye that forget God, left he teare you in pieces, and there be none to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you,</hi> Pſalm 50. 22. O remember that your life is not ſo long to day as it was yeſterday, and that though the Sunne <hi>times</hi> meaſure did once ſtand ſtill, yet time it ſelfe ever paſſed forward, and did neither ſtand with the Suns ſtanding, nor return with the Suns returning.</p>
            <p>The laſt branch that ſhould now be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto, is the <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> of this happineſſe which is both full and ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory: the <hi>matter</hi> of it is GODS <hi>face</hi> or <hi>likeneſſe,</hi> which is commonly termed by the School, <hi>faelicitas objectiva,</hi> objective happineſs: the <hi>manner</hi> of enjoying it, is by <hi>beholding the face of God,</hi> which is by them alſo called <hi>faelicitas formalis,</hi> formall happineſs. Mans objective happineſs li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth wholly out of himſelfe, and out of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very creature, and the more he fixeth his happineſs upon the object without him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:100568:26"/> the more happy and excellent he is; for as the eye is perfected by light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, ſo is the ſoule by God. But yet ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, not God abſtracted and ſimply conſidered, is mans happineſſe; but God enjoyed and looked upon as God, with whom he hath perfect union and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, is that which makes up mans formall happineſs. And this is that viſion and frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God which <hi>David</hi> faith when he awakes he ſhall be ſatisfied with. But I muſt of neceſſity wave what I intended to ſpeak of this point, having already excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (I feare) the time, that ſhould confine and terminate this Exerciſe.</p>
            <p>It is I know expected, that I ſhould ſpeak ſomewhat concerning this worthy Lady, the Lady <hi>Honor Viner,</hi> whoſe ſad fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals we now celebrate; but it hath ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been my cuſtome on ſuch occaſions to add a long <hi>Panegyrick</hi> to a <hi>Sermon,</hi> the end of this meeting being rather to inſtruct and counſel the living, then to commend the dead. Yet do I not with others think
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:100568:26"/> it wholy unlawful to give a due teſtimony to the dead, in mentioning ſuch things of their life and converſation, as may be uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful patterns to the living for their imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. If we look into the Ancients, we ſhall find them mingling the praiſes of their friends with their ſorrowful mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings over them. Thus <hi>Ambroſe</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends <hi>Saturus</hi> his worth as well as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plores his loſs, the ſame doth <hi>Nazianzen</hi> for <hi>Gorgonia</hi> his ſiſter, <hi>Austin</hi> for <hi>Nebridius</hi> his friend, and <hi>Bernard</hi> for <hi>Gervaſius.</hi> The great miſcarriage that hath brought this way both under ſuſpition and cenſure, hath been the golden commendations that ſome have beſtowed upon worthleſs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as if they did make it their profeſſed art to garniſh Tombes and Sepulchres, But though Tombes may receive an addition of beauty from colours laid upon them, yet pearls do not, they ſhine beſt not by a borrowed but by their native luſtre: And ſuch an one is ſhe of whom I am now ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king whoſe own reall endowments and qualifications will more commend her,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:100568:27"/> then adſcititious and ſtudied praiſes. I ſhall therefore give you a plain and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine character of what ſhe was, which in brief is this.</p>
            <p>She was one in whom many vertues did meet, which made her truly amiable. As a <hi>wife</hi> ſhe was a rich bleſſing to him to whom God had for many yeers given her; She was both as <hi>Ezekiels</hi> wife, the <hi>deſire of his eyes;</hi> &amp; as <hi>Solomons</hi> vertuous woman, the <hi>repoſe of his heart,</hi> &amp; did fully deſerve that praiſe which is given by him <hi>Prov.</hi> 31. 11. that <hi>the heart of her husband doth ſafely truſt in her: ſo that he ſhall have no need of ſpoile.</hi> She ſo managed domeſticall affaires, as that by her prudence his care was eaſed, and all meet ſupplies fully furniſhed. As a <hi>mother</hi> ſhe had moſt tender affections, which yet were governed with wiſdom and diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and unto others whoſe relation ſtood at a further diſtance, ſhe was (as I know themſelves will alwaies readily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge) a mother in <hi>love</hi> rather then a mother in <hi>law:</hi> ſuch an one whom few will be found to equall, much leſſe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:100568:27"/> As a <hi>friend,</hi> ſhe was affable, and cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, without haughtineſs or pride, and reall without guile. But as the watering of the Diamond though it give a luſtre to it, doth yet adde little or nothing to its value: ſo all morall perfections, though they ſet off and beautifie a Chriſtian, yet not they, but true piety doth give unto him a reall worth. What therefore ſhe was in this, as well as in the other, you ſhall ſee both by her way and practice.</p>
            <p>In works of mercy ſhe had an <hi>open hand,</hi> and a <hi>tender heart,</hi> but yet her charity run with a ſtill and ſilent ſtream: great and deep rivers that pay a large tribute to the Sea, empty themſelves oftimes into it in a more ſtill manner then the petty and ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low brookes; and ſo did ſhe diffuſe her bounty with far leſſe noiſe then many that <hi>give little</hi> and <hi>boaſt much.</hi> What ſhe did in this kind was not to get her ſelf a name, but to do the poor good.</p>
            <p>Of private duties ſhe was a conſtant ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver, making Religion the work of her <hi>Cloſet,</hi> as well as of the <hi>Church. Grande eſt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:100568:28"/> Chriſtianum eſſe non videri:</hi> It is a great thing (ſaith <hi>Jerom</hi>) to be a Chriſtian, not to ſeem one; and there is no character that doth better evidence the reality of profeſſion in any, then a conſciencious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of unſeen and ſecret duties, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in theſe times in which Religion ſhoots forth into <hi>leaves</hi> rather then into <hi>fruit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for her eſteem both of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Ordinances and the Diſpenſers of them, the two contrary affections of <hi>ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> and <hi>joy</hi> which of late had viſible ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings in her, ſhall be the preſent teſtimony. She was to my knowledge much affected with the ſad breach that God had made upon this place, by taking from it an able and faithfull Paſtor by the ſtroak of death; and was alſo not a little ſenſible of the mercy of God in providing again ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily for it. And for her affection to the Word, I ſhall now let paſſe her conſtant attendance on it on the Lords day, and ſhall briefly adde a paſſage that ſince my preaching came to my knowledge from
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:100568:28"/> him that can beſt tell, and that is this: She expreſſed herſelfe to be very glad that he was purpoſed to caſe himſelfe of ſuch burdens as had hitherto lain upon him in his calling, and to draw his buſineſſe into a narrower compaſſe: For now (ſaith ſhe) I hope you and I ſhall heare more Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and frequent more Lectures then before. A ſpeech it is, which if ſome that have time and leiſure would ſeriouſly think of, their <hi>life</hi> would prove more <hi>uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> and their <hi>death</hi> more <hi>comfortable.</hi> But not many weeks after ſhe had thus ſpoken, and pleaſed herſelfe with the hopes of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying ſuch happy opportunities, it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God to put a ſudden period to her life, which yet was no other then what that infirmity with which ſhe conflicted had once threatned, ſome of her friends feared, and her ſelfe expected; who ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> leave them on the ſudden. Such indeed was the blow, as that it took from her the opportunities that others have in lingring ſickneſſes of expreſſing themſelves; but
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:100568:29"/> though they be wanting, yet Gods hand on her ſpeaks to us, and bids to keep our Lamps burning, and our garments girt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout us, becauſe we know not at what houre our Lord will come.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:100568:29"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
